<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>NAHID AKBAR</title>
  
  <subtitle>another weird engineer</subtitle>
  <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://nahidakbar.net/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-31T02:34:10.319Z</updated>
  <id>http://nahidakbar.net/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Nahid Akbar</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="http://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Delegate to Empower - Educational</title>
    <link href="http://nahidakbar.net/2018/01/30/2018-01-30/"/>
    <id>http://nahidakbar.net/2018/01/30/2018-01-30/</id>
    <published>2018-01-30T07:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-01-31T02:34:10.319Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This educational is from toastmastersleadership excellence series.Purpose of this series is for all of us to becomebetter at leadership.</p><p>I have not picked this topic becauseI think I know the most about this topic.I have picked it becauseI have more horror stories to sharewhere I&#39;ve seen examples of this beingdone poorly and I have recognisedthat I myself have a lot to learnin this area.</p><h3 id="Why-delegate"><a href="#Why-delegate" class="headerlink" title="Why delegate?"></a>Why delegate?</h3><p>We delegate for three reasons:</p><ul><li>To free our own time. We may not have the time or may want to spend time selectively on areas and projects we went to develop of.</li><li>To get things done faster. There may be cases where delegation is feasible. For example, when you have a very complex ad-hoc process, delegation may slow things down instead. However, where it is feasible, doing things in a team may help get things done faster.</li><li>To other give people development opportunities.</li></ul><h3 id="What-is-delegation"><a href="#What-is-delegation" class="headerlink" title="What is delegation?"></a>What is delegation?</h3><p>Definitions of delegation must have two aspects:</p><p>First is the transfer of responsibility.Delegation here is distinguished from training or supervision.While those activities and ideas have value, delegation is distinctlydifferent in that the responsibility for the outcomeis transferred to the person delegated.We might be training or supervising someone closelywhere they perform tasks according to our instructionto learn something.However, in these cases, should the endeavour fail, the responsibilityfor failure should go to the trainer or the supervisor.</p><p>This leads nicely to the second aspect - empowerment to accomplishgoals.This is where delegation is distinguished from things likemicromanagement.When we are closely supervising someoneand they have done exactly as we have told them to the best of their ability,they can not blamed when the endeavour fails.When we delegate something to someone,it implies that they have them all the decision makingauthority over everything that needs to be influencedto accomplish the set task.This is the aspect of empowerment.</p><p>An example of this where these aspectsare absent might be that micromanagerwho after making you responsible fora project tries to influence everysmall detail of the project.Another example might bean organisation where youmight be responsible for a projectbut getting your tasks done requiresapprovals from a manager higher in the chain.</p><p>There are times where this might be necessary.I had a year 10 work experience student couple of years ago.I tried to be a good manager and not a micromanager.At least initially, and delegated them some tasks.I left him alone for an entire day.I was a little bit impressed by his resume and what he said.He had published an app in the appstore.I have yet to publish an app in the appstore. Never had a work or hobby project that involved doing that.But of course, as I had learned, a year 10 student is not half as good as they think they are.I discovered on day two that not only did he not accomplishanything, he was making some really stupid mistakes in thelittle progress he had made.So there are times where you may need tomicromanage things a little.</p><p>However, I would also argue that there are better ways of doing it.My current manager does it really well.It might be partially because he does not have a lot of time for me.If he received any signals where he thinks I might be goingoff track on a project,he suggests that I hold a project reviewor informally talk with another colleague on a different team.You can encourage them to seek feedback.For example, I have asked my mentor to be brutal if she sees anything wrong withwhat I do.I was going to ask her to do it but the way the conversation flowed at the time,it was almost as if she put the words inmy mouth.These work a lot better the the manager barging in and start micromanagingwhatever respect you might have for your manage out of your system.</p><h3 id="When-to-delegate"><a href="#When-to-delegate" class="headerlink" title="When to delegate?"></a>When to delegate?</h3><p>There is a section in the educational material on barriers to delegation.And this section corresponds to that.But instead of going through the points, I want to give you a frameworkfor thinking about it. It is called the situational leadership model whichlooks something like this:</p><p><figure class="figure"><img src="/contents/2018-01-30/situational.png" alt="From https://www.kenblanchard.com"><figcaption class="figure__caption">From https://www.kenblanchard.com</figcaption></figure></p><p>This model splits people in terms of two variables. First is the level of commitmentwhere people are put into two categories - highly committed (bottom half) andnot so committed (top half). Second variable is their level of competencewhere people are also put into two categories - highly capable (left half)and the highly incapable (right half). This model suggeststhat people usually vary across the spectrum in terms of these twovariables and different strategies work for different people.</p><p>Delegation here only works for people who are highly committedand are highly capable (the bottom left quadrant).If they are highly capable but is not committed, you have to get theirmotivation level up by supportive/participate behaviour (top left quadrant).If they are highly committed but they are not as competent,you can exhibit telling/directing behaviour (bottom right).This is where micromanagement shines.If they are neither committed nor capable, you have to eithercoach them or sell things to them.</p><p>The handout gives some other points which you can put intothis framework and talks about some more like insecurity and selfishnesson behalf of the leader. But I want to talk about another pointthat is not in the handout. That is, you can sometimes destroy a good teamby delegating poorly.I will give two examples. One somewhat artificial andanother from my current team.</p><p>First example is from a game I play called left for dead 2.Don&#39;t shut your brain off. This example has nothing to do with computer gaming.It is a computer game that is designed in a way where youhave to work in a team of 4 to survive a zombie apocalyptic scenario.If you don&#39;t have a good team like an incompetent team or dysfunctional team,you quickly die.Depending on the chinning, sometimes you can make do if you have one or two members who are highlycompetent.So one night I was playing in a game in a team of three.We were all highly competent.In fact, we were competing within the team to see who can get the highest score.In term literature, you could say that this was an example of a highly performingself organising team.Then this guy comes along to join us as the fourth member.And he suddenly starts using mic.He starts telling everyone what we should do moments after we decide in our headthat we are going to do.We has trying to play &quot;Mr. Leader&quot; as he saw his role was andother team members were extremely annoyed by that.I knew this was the case when he got into trouble andno one decided to come to his aid until it has too late.At this point, he abruptly rage quit. He left the team.</p><p>The second example would be something like my current work example.We have a team what you could also say is a highly performing self organising team.The team consists of three specialists, I being one of them, and a project manager.It is not a team where the leader is playing &quot;Mr leader&quot; and getting thingsdone through delegation or micromanagement.We don&#39;t need that.In fact, in 99% of the time, out project managers will simply gowhat is going on with you and is there anything I can help with.We are all proactive and self managing and we delegate things toher and we delegate things to each other.We talk to each other and get things done.Everyone in the team performs a leadership role.</p><p>If you are ever in an environment like that, don&#39;t try and ruin it byunnecessarily trying to delegate things or playing the micromanager.So it is important to think about when not to delegate thingsas leader as much as when to delegate things.</p><h3 id="How-to-effectively"><a href="#How-to-effectively" class="headerlink" title="How to effectively?"></a>How to effectively?</h3><p>First step in effective delegation is periodisation.Simply decide what needs to be delegated.As we have been discussing, not all work can be delegated.You may not have the right team members and you may not have the right tasks.Identify the ones that can be delegated.</p><p>Second step is matching availability to capability.Decide whom to delegate to.We have talked about the situational leadership model.These can help inform what strategy to pursue in gettingtasks done. You may choose to decide thatsomething is not best delegated. Maybe you instead decideto coach a motivated team member instead through the processinstead. Some people also suggest do it yourself firstso you can describe the objectives clearly.</p><p>Third step is assigning responsibility.It is important to make the assignment clear and specific.If you read the educational material, it willask you fully describe the task and processand identify training needs and resourcesand everything.I personally don&#39;t like this style of task allocation.This stems from a style of thinking originatedin the 1900s in America where the managers had toget a workforce of largely uneducated workforceto do tasks and not reduce quality of products.If you allocate tasks this way, you team will beunhappy and unsatisfied with their job etc.I think it works better if you clearly specifythe objectives that needs to accomplished.So they are free to reach the objectivehowever they want to.</p><p>Fourth step is measuring performance.Autonomy, as we&#39;ve discussed is very important.They need to be able to solve problems bythemselves and be creative and all that.However, being completely indifferent to progresstowards objectives is also an anti-pattern.You need to make sure that progress is being made.As my first mentor taught me many years ago:You need to always ask the question: is thistaking me where I want to go?Is there a better way?</p><p>Final step is giving credit and not blaming them so muchshould the endeavour fail.Feedback giving is not a foreign concept to us toastmasters.We know about the sandwich technique.It is important to cultivate a culture of feedback givingin your team.Not just once a year during performance reviews and what not.And I think it starts by you asking your team:how can i do this better?When things go well, you need to give credit to your teammembers publicly.This will encourage them to be more proactive.And when things don&#39;t go well, you need to not public blame them.Give feedback in private.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;This educational is from toastmasters
leadership excellence series.
Purpose of this series is for all of us to become
better at leadershi
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Weight Management For Adutls</title>
    <link href="http://nahidakbar.net/2017/12/26/2017-12-26/"/>
    <id>http://nahidakbar.net/2017/12/26/2017-12-26/</id>
    <published>2017-12-26T07:40:50.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-01-12T01:01:22.435Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Disclaimer: This article is for you if you are an adult andconventional wisdom has not been working for you in keepingyou within healthy weight range.I am not a Doctor.I just like to play one in the internet.The advise I&#39;ll give here may conflict with official ones.Follow at your own risk.That being said, the advise I&#39;ll give here are the ones that work for me.</p><p>I&#39;ve never had a weight problem growing up.I grew up on high carb diet living on refined sugar.I refused to eat anything else.Before my teens. my default meal would be somethingalong the lines of rice, milk and sugar mixed with somekind of fruit (like banana or mango).I ate that every day of my life for years.If I ate like that now, I&#39;ll probably kill myself withina year.However, I was not overweight.In fact, I was very very skinny.I as was as skinny as children of my age group get.Weight and food weren&#39;t things on my mind.Someone else was always responsible for feeding me.I was fed breakfast, lunch and dinner.</p><p>It wasn&#39;t much of a problem during my teens either.My diet did not change all that well.I started to appreciate some of the other tasteslike umami that comes from meat and pasta andsour foods and other fruits etc.I was a little bit over weight but it was not a problem.I was growing.I growing a lot more than I was widening.Weight was not in my mind back then but food probably was.I ate and I ate.There was nothing else to to do but to study and to eat.Perks of having asian parents.</p><p>It started becoming a problem when I was an adult.This was after I had stopped growing.I started widening instead.It was early 20s.I didn&#39;t think of much of it at the time.I was eating to the recommended guidelines.The 2 fruit and 5 vegetable crap.I was away from home then to attend university in Sydney.I was eating out with friends.I started drinking around then.I was having sugary soda with every meal.I started drinking coffee.These were the fashionable things to do.</p><p>I started taking it seriously one afternoon.I was struck with sudden chest pain.I could not stand or walk.It hurt.It was bad.I seriously thought I was gonna die.I went to a doctor.He laughed.He told me to diet and exercise.Those were foreign words to me.I had to google up what he meant by diet.</p><p>Fast forward 10 years, I am still alive.I don&#39;t have chest pains any more.I managed to pick up a sport.Something I really like.I go to gym.I diet from time to time.I think I have a very good handle over my health now.But, reflecting on what I do now, I did not always do what I do now.I researched and followed a lot of advise that did not work for me.Things written in diet and nutrition websites and fitness magazines.If you can relate to being in the same boat, this post is for you.Tips I&#39;ll give here are ones that I&#39;ve found to better my health.I&#39;ll discuss tips for making the most extreme of diets work.I&#39;ll also discuss the ones that will make them not required.Here they are:</p><h3 id="Forget-Weight-Management"><a href="#Forget-Weight-Management" class="headerlink" title="Forget Weight Management"></a>Forget Weight Management</h3><p><strong>TLDR: Forget weight management! Track body fat percentage/kilogramsinstead.20% or under is probably a healthy body fat target for bothmales and females.</strong></p><p>First couple of tips are related to getting your facts straight.There is a lot of misinformation out there.Perhaps misinformation is not the right word to use here.I am sure they work for some peopleFor those people, no matter what they do, they will probably stay healthy.Maybe they genetically gifted or are some other kind of freak of nature.Maybe they do something else that prevents them from gaining weight.Important thing is that, since these advises do not work for you, you get to stop following them.The biggest bs I&#39;ve encountered is the weight myth.</p><p>There is something called the BMI.Given your height, it will spit out a healthy weight range for you tobe in.If you are above it, you need to lose some weight.If you are below it, you need to gain some.It is the biggest load of crap out there. Here is why:</p><p>First, weight does not matter.Pick someone like Arnold Schwarzenegger for example.He is he is probably a freak of nature. But he is an important freak of nature.His height is 188cm.According to official guidelines, his weight should be 53.5 - 72kg for him to be healthy.How much does he weight? 107 kg.According to official guidelines, he is above and beyond obese.</p><p>Is he though?No chance in hell. He probably still has over 72 kilos of pure muscleand dense bones despite being 70 now. I am not asking you to become a bodybuilder.However, those are things that you want to have to improve your immune system andfor good ageing.If you are sick all the time from trivial diseases, try making your bones more dense your bones with some high impact training.Will work a lot better than prescription drugs.Also, if you don&#39;t want to curl up into a weak old man by the time you are 40,put some time into gym every once in a while or pick up some kind of sport.This is especially important if you have a desk job like mine.</p><p>Second, some weights just don&#39;t matter.I can, for example, go on a yoyo diet right now.I will probably lose 1-2 kg a day over the next few days until I exhaust mymental strength or die from dehydration.How? My body will lose slowly sodium and other important mineralsand I will lose a lot of water weight.Once I start eating, I will gain back my weight almost immediately.What was the point of this exercise?Nothing at all.Did your waistline shrink? Nope.Most people give up long before their liver runs out of stored glucoseand their body actually adapts to burning fat.No improvement of health.Most people who diet a little bit here or there never do.They learn hate themselves in the process and blame their genes.</p><p>Does it mean that we should not keep track of our health?Absolutely not.If you have nothing better to track, measure you weight.That is your MVP.If you eat bullshit written in official guidelines, don&#39;t exercise and live a sedantary lifestyle,the BMI guide is probably as good as any.</p><p>However, if you care about your health and exercise or play some kind of sport,upgrade your measurement to this number: your body fat percentage.If you like a measurement in kilograms, convert that number intothe number of kilograms of fat your body has.It is the only fitness number that matters.</p><p>Why? if you have a lot of fat in your body, you probably also have a fatty liver.And you are probably at the risk of what doctors refer to as weight related diseases.And other than muscle and bone density, that is the difference betweena regular old 70 year old fat man and someone like Arnold.He has a very low body fat content which highlights his body&#39;s definitionand makes him look younger. Here is a visual guide for your reference:</p><p><figure class="figure"><img src="/contents/2017-12-26/body-fat-percentage.jpg" alt=""></figure></p><p>Also, for the yoyo diet example, when you lose 5kgs of water weightand feel like stabbing yourself in the eye in the process,you learn to not repeat such exercises in futility when you measurethe right metrics.</p><p>There are a lot of ways to measure this. There are calipers, DEXA scans,biometric scales. I personally don&#39;t recommend invasive techniqueslike DEXA. Although, it is probably the most accurate measure,you are practically X-raying your body every time youwant to get a measure. I like to save that kind of radiationexposure for special occasions like when I break a leg or something.</p><p>If you don&#39;t measure, you are practically in the dark.If you are not in control with accurate measurements,you&#39;ll easily fool yourself with shit advise written innutritionist websites and fitness magazines.Don&#39;t waste your time.Start measuring.Experiment with your food and your body and yourexercises.See what works for you and follow them.Don&#39;t do things that does not work for you.The other part is, once you start making the right kind of progress, nothing will motivate you and help you stay on track than yourself seeing your own progress.It works a lot better than telling all your friends about it.</p><h3 id="Stop-Being-A-Vegan"><a href="#Stop-Being-A-Vegan" class="headerlink" title="Stop Being A Vegan"></a>Stop Being A Vegan</h3><p>Have you ever tried to be a vegetarian or vegan for improving health?Chances are that you have that thin/attractive friendwho claims that their health is attributed to being a vegan.</p><p>I am not gonna deny it.You could probably lose weight by being a vegan if your bodybecame malfunctioned in a way for that to happen.I can&#39;t think of any other reasons as to why it would work.I, like you, know way too many fat vegans.Most people who claim that it improves health were eithermalnutritioned of essential minerals prior to being a veganor have one of those freak of nature bodies.I have also been there and done it.I can confirm that it is simply superstition.Much like a lot of other superstitious mumbo jumbo a lot of people who would be suckers for being vegan would believe in.Astrology for example.</p><p>If it works for you, then great.I&#39;d claim that it would work for you even if you didn&#39;t.However, it most probably won&#39;t.And don&#39;t damage your health permanently in some way by following weird diets.My recommendation: eat everything. That includes vegetables.</p><p>My one rule for diets is no carbs. Works a lot better for my body than no fatsor no meat. But I break it religiously. Went for a holiday to Thailand recently.Had mango sticky rice almost every day I was there. Contrary to a lot of popularwisdom, I don&#39;t eat lean any more. My diet is full of fats.My favourite dish is pork belly stuffed in eggplants.I fry my vegetables in coconut oil and salted butter and angus fat and duck fat.And I am as healthy as I&#39;ve ever been in the history of my health.</p><h3 id="Stop-Exercising"><a href="#Stop-Exercising" class="headerlink" title="Stop Exercising"></a>Stop Exercising</h3><p><strong>TLDR: exercise for improving health; not burning fat.</strong></p><p>Have you ever heard of fat burning exercises?Every single treadmill I&#39;ve seen has a chart that shows a fat burning zone.Apparently, if your heart rate is within a certain range, it willburn fat instead of the glucose in your bloodstream and those stored in your liver.Complete utter non-sense.</p><p>I did these fat burning exercises for years expecting them to reduce my waistline.They never worked.Also, don&#39;t think that just by gaining a little bit of muscle thoughexercising, you are gonna magically lose all your fats.If you have weight problems, chances are that your gains won&#39;t even be visible.Soon, you will go back to blaming your genes and start avoiding your non obesefriends to make yourself try to feel better.</p><p>If you are gonna exercise, do it for the right reasons.Those are: improving strength/flexibility/speed/endurance/bone density etc.Those can improve the quality of your life even if you are fat.But don&#39;t do it for burning fat. Why? Because 99.99% of fat gains/losses are due to nutrition.I&#39;ve heard bs like muscles will help you metabolise more energy and hence help burn fat.Unless you have muscles the size of Arnold and adjusted eating, I&#39;d say not so much.Exercising can greatly enhance your fat loss efforts if your eating behaviour is correct.However, if you are doing the same old thing, exercising won&#39;t help much.In fact, if you are overweight, you are more likely to injure yourself exercising.So before you turn your fat down to a safe range, you probably shouldn&#39;t get too crazy.</p><h3 id="Eliminate-Stress"><a href="#Eliminate-Stress" class="headerlink" title="Eliminate Stress"></a>Eliminate Stress</h3><p>This one should be a no brainer.Stress adversely affects your health.I&#39;ve heard things like stress turns your body alkaline and increases your natural insulin level.I don&#39;t know. I am not a doctor.However, I have observed that stress causes me lose sleep.And losing sleep makes me hungry.</p><h3 id="Control-Eating-Times"><a href="#Control-Eating-Times" class="headerlink" title="Control Eating Times"></a>Control Eating Times</h3><p><strong>TLDR: Eat Less Often</strong></p><p>If you have weight problems, there is a very good chance that you eat too muchtoo often. The former here is less of a problem than the latter.Instead of going on crazy low calorie diets, or restricting the types of food you eat,simply reduce the number of times a day you eat and see what happens.</p><p>If you are fat, you probably have developed insulin resistance.Every time you eat, your body releases insulin.This is a hormone whose job it is to stop burningfat and storing glucose in bloodstream as fat.Think of it as a relay that governs whether you gain or lose fat.Ask your doctor if you can burn fat while you have insulin in your body.The answer he will give you is a big fat NO.Other than not being able to burn fat when this hormone is present,nothing good is ever associated prolonged levels of insulin in your body.Things commonly discussed are some cancers, bad skin etc.You also get to develop insulin resistance.This is where your body ends up releasing a lot more insulinthan necessary and causes your body to store a lot more fat.This eventually leads to type 2 diabetes.</p><p>In the west, people usually have three meals a day: breakfast, lunch and dinner.People who are fat usually also have snacks in between.There is a &quot;sugar&quot; culture here in Australia where people think thatyou need a constant supply of energy and nutrients through eatingin your body for it to work.Nothing could be further from the truth.</p><p>This comes from taking a inorganic/washing machine view tohuman body.A washing machine can not operate without a constant supply of energy.However, human body does not quite work the same way.Your body is a lot smarter than the doctors and nutritionistswho think this way.Your body stores energy and essential nutrients it needsin its storage in case you run low.If you stop eating and drinking, it will probably take you over a week<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Starvation" target="_blank" rel="noopener">before you die</a>.If you have access to water and essential minerals, it will be months before you diefrom starvation.</p><p>Think of it this way: before the agricultural revolution, humans did not haveconstant supply of food.People went through periods of feast and famine.How did they survive?We evolved to not live on 2 fruits and 5 vegetables a day.When you start living on 2 fruits and 5 vegetables a day, you startto have developed world diseases like cancer and diabetes.I will confess to not having had a slice of fruit in over a month and I am fine.We will go more into that in controlling what you eat. However, the first stepand the most beneficial one is controlling how often you eat.</p><p>Eat as much as you think you need but at the very least, reduce your eating timesto 3 meals a day.Without reducing the amount of food you eat, there are a few ways to furtherimproving insulin issues:</p><p>First one is to reduce the number of meals.Unless you are 12, breakfast is probably not the most important meal of the day.If you are not hungry, skip it.There is no medical basis for the western 3 meal eating pattern.Your body will store everything it needs for days and months.Instead of eating more often, eat more when you are hungry.</p><p>Second is reducing eating times to a certain number of hours a day.There is the famous fast 5 diet when all the eating of the day is donewithin a 5 hour window in the day. I&#39;ve seenversions where the eating window is 8 hours or less than 5 hours.The principle is the same.What you need to know about these diets is that they work like magic.It restricts the times of a day where there is insulin in your bloodstream to a few hours.It probably slowly reverses insulin resistance.I&#39;ve also observed that effect of alcohol and other medicationincreases when you are doing this form of diets.</p><p>Third, I&#39;ve also read that regular exercising lowers insulin levels in your body.I have yet to experiment with it but it seems plausible.Exercising would lower blood glucose.It would not make sense for the body to have high levels of insulin then.</p><p>Lastly, if you are going to restrict the amount of times you eator skip a meal, the best one to do is the one before sleep.During the first cycle of deep sleep, your body releases a lot of growthhormone.That helps your body grow, perform essential repairs and improve skin etc.It is the largest fat burning hormone out there.Effect of that greatly lessens if you have high levels of insulin in your bodyat the time.If you want better health, have dinner a couple of hours you go to bed.Instead of snacking before bed, eat more during dinner.Add some essential fats to your food.It&#39;ll make you less hungry.</p><h3 id="Control-What-Type-Of-Food-You-Eat"><a href="#Control-What-Type-Of-Food-You-Eat" class="headerlink" title="Control What Type Of Food You Eat"></a>Control What Type Of Food You Eat</h3><p><strong> TLDR: remove bad carbohydrates from diet; start consuming fats </strong></p><p>This section is for you if you have come as far as you can by eating less times a day.If you think that you have reached some kind of stasis with your body fat percentagewith eating only once a day and you feel like you are still unhealthy.Well, it is time to start experimenting with food types.Most people will not need to come this far.But if you do, this is what will work:</p><p>You will never have these foods again: sugar, anythingwith fructose, simple/starchy carbohydrates. Seriously.</p><p>First, if you are gonna do this properly, no sugar means absolutely no sugar.It means no brown sugar. It means no honey.There is absolutely no reason to have refined sugar.If you need to sweeten, go for artificial sweeteners.Yes some of the artificial sweeteners may have temporary adverse effects,e.g. cause diphtheria, when consumed in large quantities.Even if that happened, it is probably avery small price to pay if you really want to have that cake and don&#39;twant to stab yourself in the eye afterwards.That is, only if you think you want to come this far.I don&#39;t. But I have experimented with it. And I know that it works.So far, I haven&#39;t had a bad experience with Erythritol.Although, be warned that these artificial sweetnercompounds are of different sizes to sucrose.Taste aside, they will act differently to sugar.So you may need to adjust you recipe when cooking with these.</p><p>Second, no fruits.There is absolutely no reason to consume fruits.Fruits have vitamin c? Veges have a lot more.Fruits have potassium? Veges have a lot more.Fruits have fibre? Veges have a lot more.I think you get the pattern.If you need conviencing, look up the chemical compoundfor table sugar (sucrose) and look up the one for fruit sugar(fructose).You&#39;ll find to your shock that one is made of the other.If sugar is bad, both are.</p><p>Third, avoid starchy carbohydrates.No pasta - no rice - no brown rice - not even wholemeal bs.You are most probably familiar with glycemic index (GI).Nutritionists usually advise that lower GI food is good.Yes, they are. It is because lower GI carbs are usually more complex,more mineral rich that take longer for the body to absorb stuff out of.That is - it provides energy for you longer.It is probably true but there is also some BS here.Your liver stores enough glycogen to last 2-3 days.If you exercise heavily, you will still last over a day.You don&#39;t need to eat low GI food for slow release of energy.That part is BS.Starchy carbohydrates are also foods we did not havemuch of before the agricultural revolution.I am not gonna sprout bullshit like eat in moderation.If you need to come this far to get your health sorted thenyour body needs extreme adjustments to get back to the righttrack.Avoid all these foods altogether.They don&#39;t agree with your body.</p><p>What about Asians? They eat a lot of carbs. Well, what about them.Check their latest national health stats.As they adapt western eating habits more and more,they are on their way to becoming just as unhealthy as the rest of us in terms of developed world diseases.I&#39;ve read some BS article suggesting that apparently the Japanesehave some gene mutation that let them absorb carbohydrates more efficiently.I don&#39;t know about that.I am very used to seeing Japanese faces and they look just as fat and ugly to meas all the other races in the world.</p><p>What to eat instead? If you are up to here, it is time to start burning fat.There is only one condition that need to be fulfilled for burning fat:Your liver&#39;s stored energy reserve must be empty.Well there are two.You need to not have insulin in your blood stream.When it is empty and your body needs to use energy, it will start burning fat.Best way to kick start into that state is doing some form of fasting where youdon&#39;t eat any food for 2-3 days. Exercising during this periodcan speed up the process.If you get that bad headache, it is due to your body losing water and sodium.I usually start taking a cocktail of 98% water mixed with a little bit of salt, lime and apple cidar vinegar at this point.You will usually feel nauseous when you start burning fat/ketones instead of glucose.Napping will help.There is a common misconception that your brain needs glucose to function.It does not.Your brain will be a lot sharper when you are burning ketones instead of glucose.There will just initially be minor discomfort due to low energy and glucose withdrawalwhen your body is switching over what it is burning.</p><p>Once you start burning fat, you will want to keep burning fat.There is a lot of literature out there in ketogenic diet which you can follow.Basically, there is a second scale called the insulin index which measureshow much insulin is released in response to the food you consume,You want to consume food to keep insulin release in your body tothe bare minimum. Typically, you will consume a lot of fats, some good qualityvegetables and some protein.It is important to not consume too much protein as the body can convert excessprotein into glucose which can increase insulin.Consuming fats will also help you feel more full and stay full for longer.Be careful as to not consume too much calories.If you eat too much, you will still gain fat.</p><p>The other thing to keep in mind is that there is a limit to how muchfat you can burn in a day. It is tied to the release of growth hormone duringsleep and how much you breathe. When everything is running smoothly,I&#39;ve experienced loosing up to 300-500grams of fat a day (not water weight or muscle).If you want to measure how much fat youare burning, you can get yourself a breath acetone meter which is a by productof the fat burning process.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: This article is for you if you are an adult and
conventional wisdom has not been working for you in keeping
you within health
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Leadership Archetypes</title>
    <link href="http://nahidakbar.net/2017/12/24/2017-12-24/"/>
    <id>http://nahidakbar.net/2017/12/24/2017-12-24/</id>
    <published>2017-12-24T07:40:50.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-01-12T00:30:50.391Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Earlier, I mentioned my favourite definition of leadership being somethingalong the lines of:</p><blockquote><p>someone assumes a leadership role when someone decides there is a problem, a need or an injustice and takes action to solve the problem, fulfil the need or correct the injustice</p></blockquote><p>From this view, leadership archetypes are the different rolespeople take in fulfilling a need or solving a problem or correcting an injustice.There seems to be several schools of thoughts in terms of what these archetypes are.I&#39;ll do my best consolidate some of the positive ones here:</p><h3 id="Teacher-Mentor-Coach"><a href="#Teacher-Mentor-Coach" class="headerlink" title="Teacher / Mentor / Coach"></a>Teacher / Mentor / Coach</h3><p>In fulfilling need for development, these are people who develop other people.Maybe they have travelled the path before.Maybe they have experimented with the subject matter or they have more experience.Or maybe they are just good at coaching or keeping you motivated.</p><p>This requires a special kind of skill.Being good at something does not automatically mean that someone are good at teaching/mentoring other people.Also, being able to teach something to others does not necessary mean that someone is very good at that skill.They don&#39;t have to be either.Those are independent skills to acquire and are both very valuable.</p><p>In my experience, these people will talk to you about your goals and hopesand dreams etc and will enable you in your development.</p><h4 id="Student-Mentee-Athlete"><a href="#Student-Mentee-Athlete" class="headerlink" title="Student / Mentee / Athlete"></a>Student / Mentee / Athlete</h4><p>This archetype/role is one that I think does not get mentioned in a lot of literature.This is the exact opposite of the teacher/mentor role -the proactive student who is in charge of their own development.</p><p>This person will go to you and ask you for your guidance and feedback.He will ask you to be their mentor etc.</p><h4 id="Learners"><a href="#Learners" class="headerlink" title="Learners"></a>Learners</h4><p>There is a third configuration to this role which I think is the best one.Teachers are greatly respected in every society.If they are not, I think there is something wrong with that society.However, I have also experienced instances where the status of the teacherand the student can be equal and of mutual interest.</p><p>I think this happens naturally where the student and the teacher are both focused on improving.They inspire each other and develop together through shared experiences.You are comrades in your journey towards improvement.I think we should be respectful and thankful to anyone who help us grow.In turn, we should help out others where we can in their growth.</p><h3 id="Father-Judge-Manager-Processor"><a href="#Father-Judge-Manager-Processor" class="headerlink" title="Father / Judge / Manager / Processor"></a>Father / Judge / Manager / Processor</h3><p>In terms of getting things done, whether it be via planning and followinga plan or the other extreme of moving towards the general direction of solution,you need people to &quot;provide oversight, control, moral guidance and caringprotection.&quot;The main characteristic of this role is the ability to oversee others.Make sure that they are moving in the right direction and thattheir cats and dogs are happy.</p><p>The &quot;father&quot; terminology obviously comes from the traditionalimage of a father figure some kind of patriarchal family setup.If you think of your team, your department, your company etc as a family,these are the people who will make sure that whatever directionyou&#39;re taking your family is not set for doom and make sure that you arekeeping track of your plan.Some literature also add a creation or direction aspect to this role but I don&#39;twant to conflate this role with some of the other I want to list whose mainfocus is those activities.My current interpretation of this archetype is a traditional/conservativemiddle manager role/wizards of operation who make sure that everyone is happyand everything is operating smoothly. They communicate and empathise. </p><p>I am not downplaying this role when I use words like traditional orconservative.This role is obviously one of the most important ones.If everyone wanted to play the role of the visionary/entrepreneurial leader allthe time, nothing would ever get done.</p><p>When I think of someone in this architype, I think of an army leader.I heard that in the US navy seals, the leader eats after everyone else.In Sun Tzu&#39;s art of war, he tells the leader to regard their soldiers as childrenso they may follow him to the ends of the earth.</p><h3 id="Warrior-Knight-Mercenary-Hero-Soldier-Engineer-Theif-Builder-Gambler"><a href="#Warrior-Knight-Mercenary-Hero-Soldier-Engineer-Theif-Builder-Gambler" class="headerlink" title="Warrior / Knight / Mercenary / Hero / Soldier / Engineer / Theif / Builder / Gambler"></a>Warrior / Knight / Mercenary / Hero / Soldier / Engineer / Theif / Builder / Gambler</h3><p>These are people who take risks and action during a crisis.I&#39;ve lumped them together because they are very similar. However are sub-architypes within these.For example:</p><ul><li>you can be a knight vs. a mercenary on the dimension of loyalty.</li><li>you can be a warrior/knight vs. shadow warrior/dark knight in terms of your regards for rules.</li><li>you can be a hero vs. a coward/bystander in terms of your decision to show courage/act independently.</li></ul><p>For me, what is characteristic of these roles are their direct connection/contribution.They are the doers. They have hold over life and death.If this was the warring states period in Japan, they would be the Samurais.If this was an R&amp;D firm, they would be the scientists and engineers.If this was a car dealership, they would be the salespeople.I&#39;d put someone who is really good at making deals into this category.They take leadership position when they decide to act in responseto some need.They are also characterised due to the direct risk they take.Whether it is in the modern era in terms of their time or in the distant past interms of their lives.</p><p>This one is probably hardest to grasp for most people. But it is not incomprehensible.Think of a modern R&amp;D organisation. Who are the leaders there? Is it thesponsors who provide research funds? Is it their CEO who provides visionsthat are vague enough to mean anything? We certainly pay him the most.Is it the middle managers who divide up the funding between their teams?They certainly like to do all the hiring and firing.Or is it the researchers and scientists who tinker with things day and night toproduce the actual results?If you ask me, it is either all of them or none of them.If you still don&#39;t get it, let&#39;s play a game I like to call: &quot;take it out and see.&quot;Which of the roles explained here can you take out and things would stillfunction? Say we fired the CEO or all the middle managers or all the scientists or all the engineers?Would things still function?You&#39;ll find that the CEO&#39;s leadership role is the least important one.</p><h4 id="Strategist-Tactician-Schemer-Spy"><a href="#Strategist-Tactician-Schemer-Spy" class="headerlink" title="Strategist / Tactician / Schemer / Spy"></a>Strategist / Tactician / Schemer / Spy</h4><p>This is sub-archetype I see that is as important as the Warrior archetype.People in these roles are usually accomplished warriors/knights or have equivalent knowledgeto be able to operate at a meta level to maximise their goals.</p><p>There are multiple levels of this. There is the high level strategy.Things like &quot;we will be customer first&quot; and &quot;we will be a collaboration hub&quot; for example.</p><p>However, there is also lower level of strategy that is much more useful/closer to real life.Some call it tactics or still lump it with strategy.For example, &quot;we will use this architecture&quot; or &quot;lets invest into to find a better solution for this&quot; or &quot;let&#39;s target this market with this product.&quot;It is when you know what you can do and how things may turn out and cleverly takepractical steps to reach a more favourable outcome.</p><p>For example, something may be ordinarily not possible.But someone may decide &quot;if we were a little bit clever and did this instead, it could work&quot; and experiment.And it may lead to a more successful outcome. Or it may not work.And you may learn that and come one step closer to solving that problem.The strategist sub-archetype here would correspond to the being clever part.Rest, I&#39;d put under the visionary archetype.</p><h3 id="Visionary-Alchemist"><a href="#Visionary-Alchemist" class="headerlink" title="Visionary / Alchemist"></a>Visionary / Alchemist</h3><p>Someone who imagines possibilities and guides/acts towards bringing them to reality.I suppose this person is one level above the person who comes up ideas and seeks validation based on it.They act on turning their ideas into reality.</p><p>I suppose you&#39;d put someone like Steve Jobs into this category.Personally, when I think of a visionary, someone like Einstein or Turing comes to mind.They did not just come up with ideas.They went with their ideas. They contributed enough to leave their name in history books.Probably a high bar to follow for someone from the modern era like Steve Jobs.I am sure he did he best.</p><p>I&#39;d put someone like an entrepreneur in this category.Maybe someone had a clever business idea.They went with it. Succeeded or not, they tried to be a leader by trying to makeit happen.</p><p>I sometimes put some of my time into a hackathon called random hacks of kindness.There, individuals called &quot;change makers&quot; pitch ideas for some kind of causeand usually over a weekend, some hackers get together to build a system or somethingthat helps further the cause. I&#39;d say those &quot;change makers&quot; are also excellentexamples of this archetypes.</p><h4 id="Revolutionary-Crusader"><a href="#Revolutionary-Crusader" class="headerlink" title="Revolutionary / Crusader"></a>Revolutionary / Crusader</h4><p>I see them as a sub-archetype. They are the same as Visionaries.They differ in that their vision conflicts with status quo / established order.</p><h3 id="Summary"><a href="#Summary" class="headerlink" title="Summary"></a>Summary</h3><p>There are plenty others. But those I believe are the main ones.People lead by a combination of:</p><ul><li>developing others,</li><li>providing oversight,</li><li>contributing time and skills, and</li><li>acting on their vision</li></ul><p>in solving a problem, fulfilling a need or correcting some injustice.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Earlier, I mentioned my favourite definition of leadership being something
along the lines of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;someone assumes a lead
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Biases That Affect Evaluations</title>
    <link href="http://nahidakbar.net/2017/12/19/2017-12-19/"/>
    <id>http://nahidakbar.net/2017/12/19/2017-12-19/</id>
    <published>2017-12-19T07:40:50.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-01-12T00:30:50.391Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Both formally and informally, we all have to perform evaluations on a daily basis.Whether it is doing someone&#39;s performance evaluation at work orchoosing which library to use for a given problem, we can&#39;t escape it.More often than not, we make errors in this due to the biases and heuristics we have learned to have.I will try to list some of those here.</p><p>I won&#39;t try to list all types of thinking errors.There was something of a masterlist compiled in a book by<a href="https://www.amazon.com/Art-Thinking-Clearly-Rolf-Dobelli/dp/0062219693" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Rolf Dobelli called &quot;The Art Of Thinking Clearly,&quot;</a>.That book is what bible would read like if it was written today.If Sun Tzu was from today&#39;s era, he would have had a chapter on it in The Art Of War.It is a must read for everyone.It just so happens that I am reading through a HR book and I amtrying to reconcile what I am learning with my past experience by reflecting on it here. So here goes:</p><h3 id="Halo-Effect"><a href="#Halo-Effect" class="headerlink" title="Halo Effect"></a>Halo Effect</h3><p>The other day our CEO gave his routine end of year Christmas speech.He was dressed very informally, grew a bit of a beard, was in a check shirt with some washed up jeans.Seeing him made a weird thought run through my head:Why did he dress like a hipster for this particular occasion?</p><p>I soon remembered that halo effect was at work.If it was a different industry, the CEO would have been right to wear an expensive suit.But, well, I work in the topmost ICT R&amp;D organisation in the country andalmost everyone in the company dresses like that.Positive things usually aren&#39;t associated with dressing up.As far as I recall, there was only once when I was asked to dress sharply.It was during a public marketing event where one of my projects were being presented.Before that, the only time I dressed up was during my job interview (being ex public service)and during my first day at work (never again).</p><p>Halo effect is our tendency to generalise domain specificcompetency across domains.In above instance, for example, people&#39;s fashion senseis being seen as an indicator of their competency.People usually associate a variety of factors to a variety of competencies.For example, tallness, attractiveness, what kind of car they drive etc.They do this because they don&#39;t know you and because they are lazy.So they set their expectation based on things that are easy to derive.</p><p>The way to not be influenced by halo effect while giving evaluations is toestablish clear performance evaluation criteria beforehand and sticking toit. Being conscious of it helps. However, there is still a probability that youryour judgement in those criteria are being swayed.</p><h3 id="Horn-Effect"><a href="#Horn-Effect" class="headerlink" title="Horn Effect"></a>Horn Effect</h3><p>Horn effect is the exact opposite of Halo effect where negative attributesof individuals are taken as an indicator of unrelated competencies negatively.For example, person X does not like D&amp;D so he must not be a good engineer.These are just as stupid as Halo Effects.</p><p>We are influenced by these biases because these heuristicsusually serve us. For example, food that smell bad are usually rottenand taste bad. However, we also need to keep in mind that they are justheuristics. If not, for example, we would never be able to taste greattasting food like Durian and Papaya if we strictly adhered by those rules.Once again, being aware of it, being realistic about it and sticking to astrict set of criteria may help mitigate some of this.</p><h3 id="Social-Proof"><a href="#Social-Proof" class="headerlink" title="Social Proof"></a>Social Proof</h3><p>This is another one of those heuristics that serve us. For example,we typically use libraries and technology that a lot of other people use or say are good.So we expect it to be good and we are usually satisfied with it either due to the product or the personeither being good or due to self fulfilment prophecy/confirmation bias.This is why we hire consultants, follow thought leaders and go to conferences etc.They tell us things that are safe and proven.</p><p>I am not saying that we should not do these things.They provide a lot of value.I could call someone who did not exploit existing wisdom to maximise his chancesa fool.What I have problems with is only following established practice and never experimenting.These will usually serve you well until when you have to step outside your me too box.For example, when you come up with something exceptional or revolutionary or innovative etc.These will only slow you down then.</p><p>In the tech sector, there are additional things like textbook examples,accepted practice, &quot;standard practice&quot;, COTS software etc which worksimilar to social proof.For example. when was the last time you built a system that was nota database backed three layered system?Sometimes, there are &quot;my way or the high way&quot; people that will penaliseyou for what they perceive to be the best solution or, worse, the only way to solve a problem.It is worse when it is done retrospectively.&quot;That was a bad decision. Why did you do things this way? It is not standard practice.&quot;If you have been practising in the industry a while and have ever tried new things,chances are that you&#39;ve heard phrases similar to this.Retrospective distortion.No!They don&#39;t get to have a say unless they were there originally and spoke forthings to be otherwise.</p><p>In machine learning, there is the concept of balancing exploration and exploitation.I think that is something that should apply universally to professional practice.When you are giving evaluations, be aware of not dismissing new or differentthings and points of view.When you are in teams with conservative and political people, be a little bitmove a little bit slowly. Be sure to frame things properly and keep them informed etc.</p><h3 id="Confirmation-Bias"><a href="#Confirmation-Bias" class="headerlink" title="Confirmation Bias"></a>Confirmation Bias</h3><p>This is one of the worst ones.</p><p>Suppose that I referred you to John and said that he is very friendly.Suppose that in your first interaction with him, he acts in an ambiguousmanner that could be interpreted to be friendly or anything else.Unless he explicitly expressed hostility, you will most likelyinterpret that as a signal to be friendly and it will reinforceyour expectation that he is friendly. What would happen if Itold you instead that he was a little bit crazy.</p><p>Few years ago, I came to think that people who write software for the JVMwere not very intelligent. How? I hung out with the wrong thought leaders.I respected their opinions and they made such opinion known to me.This is before I learned about confirmation bias and such.I, of course, have stopped building systems in java and to this date,I have not met anyone I&#39;d respect to be intelligent who wrotesoftware for JVM. Except maybe my first mentor. Well, he was also apolygot like me who programmed in whatever was necessary.In reality, whether I and them believe if JVM was trash or was the bestplatform out there is not of any consequence.The reason for that is that it is not a rule of nature.People who think that java is the best thing ever may live their entirelife and satisfy their clients by programming in java.They are of no consequence to people who think java is absolutely rubbish.They also can satisfy their clients and live their entire life withouteven knowing about the existence of java. There are plenty of other alternatives.Same thing could be said about 90% of the technologies of today.Whether you like them or hate them is of no consequence.But if you are evaluating someone else&#39;s performancebased on your inconsequential beliefs, it stops to be harmless.</p><p>More recently, someone told me that functional programming was theonly way to produce correct, robust software.Academia driven bullshit of course.Spread by the type of idiots who would have you believe thatthe only reason we have wheels is because a scientist wrote apaper to point out the possibility of wheels.This person was also a thought leader. Someone I respected.Unfortunately, this was after I had learned about confirmation bias.Sure, I have learned a great deal about functional programming sincethen including doing formal courses.I wasn&#39;t gonna dismiss it.What if it was indeed the promised holy grail?But I was also humble about it.I knew that people said similar things about OOP before.There wasn&#39;t anything particularly difficult about it.It was just using a different set of concepts than the ones I was used to using.However, I have not yet stitched over to functional programming asI have not seen any value or benefit in the change.There isn&#39;t anything revolutionary in FP that a good static code checker combinedwith minimal testing can not overcompensate for.It is not a particularly interesting programming paradigm either.So far, staying true to things I value in my professional practice, such as seeing happy clients and users,has not required it.I like to think that I am practical.I would automate away writing code if I could.So far it is the most boring aspect of my job.That being said, I&#39;d probably still use a functional programming language if there was a real need for it.For example, if I was writing code for a pacemaker or sending rockets into space.The overhead would be more than justified.</p><p>Anyways, be careful of the thoughts and opinions you have inside your head.Especially the ones you feel very strongly about.See how they influence how you evaluate others.Also, don&#39;t evaluate people negatively based on how other people might see them.Of course, bring it to their attention as part of their feedback if you are particularly concerned.</p><p>In terms of others being influenced by confirmation bias,there is not a lot you can do.Be positive, humble, friendly etc and maybe what goes around will come around.Even the nicest person in the world will have critiques.</p><h3 id="Fundamental-Attribution-Error-And-Similar-To-Me-Errors"><a href="#Fundamental-Attribution-Error-And-Similar-To-Me-Errors" class="headerlink" title="Fundamental Attribution Error And Similar To Me Errors"></a>Fundamental Attribution Error And Similar To Me Errors</h3><p>People have a tendency to explain away other&#39;s behaviour to their attributesand their own behaviour to environmental factors.For example, if Mary forgot to write a test case, it is because she lacks attention to detail.But when I forget to write a test cases, it is always because I was in a rush at the time.</p><p>This works in inverse as well.When we do something successfully, we attribute it to our characteristics.The project performed beyond expectations because of my slick project management skills.When the same thing happens for someone else, it is usually due to luck or some other situational circumstances.</p><p>This also happens at large scales in groups. E.g. different race,particular tech stack users, alumni of different universities orex colleagues of a particular company etc.Behaviour of members of other group gets explained away by their attributesand behaviours of members of our group to circumstances.This also happens to people and groups you put on pedestals.If you, for example, think that functional programmers are smarter,you will experience similar effects.If you think the opposite, you will also selectively focus on only negativeaspects of that group.</p><p>Everyone does it!It is some kind of a natural defence mechanism.Unfortunately, it clouds our evaluations, stops our own selves from improvingand stops us from having real relationships with people.It is something to be very weary of due to anotherissue called the recency error. Our brains rarely think comprehensivelyabout anything. When we evaluate people, we will most likely focuson one or two events that stood out. These things that stand out are eithervery exceptional performance or negative things. Due to the way we processinformation, business as usual things usually don&#39;t stand out as much.</p><p>So, before highlighting away past events as negative attributesof other people, consider their circumstances. Chances are thatyou could not have done any better in the situation.</p><p>And if you want to stand out in your performance reviews,cause fake panics and take credit for resolving them.I am kidding. Don&#39;t! That would be unethical.But keep a list of your accomplishments as wellas you will also forget. Something like a learning log or anengineers diary can be invaluable during reviews and things.</p><p>Another way this goes wrong is when people are put on pedestals.For example, maybe there is a rock star hire or emerging employee etc.People build up certain expectations of them.Things usually work out with help from conformation bias.However, if they mess up enough or badly, the fall breaks them inside your mind andall their negative aspects get highlighted.Another fun effect of putting people on pedestals isthe phenomenon where for one reason or another, you won&#39;t be able to outperform them.So don&#39;t put people on pedestals.Everyone are victims of their circumstances or no one is.</p><h3 id="Recency-Errors-Primacy-Errors-and-Contrast-Errors"><a href="#Recency-Errors-Primacy-Errors-and-Contrast-Errors" class="headerlink" title="Recency Errors, Primacy Errors and Contrast Errors"></a>Recency Errors, Primacy Errors and Contrast Errors</h3><p>Unless things stand out, evaluations are often done in lightof the most recent set of events and interactions that are fresh in mind.It is worse when a member or the team or something particularly stands outduring a recent crisis or something.All the evaluator can think of is that event and that personand everyone else gets unhelpful mediocre evaluations.</p><p>This happens because our brains are incapable of thinking comprehensivelyabout things. Thinking is a very slow process. It is natural to forget things over timeand you will never remember everything you need to make give good comprehensive evaluations.</p><p>What is the cure? If you are in a position where youknow that you will have to give evaluations and feedback,take notes and use checklists throughout their performance.If you can&#39;t, you should not giving them evaluations.</p><h3 id="Leniency-Errors-Strictness-Error-Error-Of-Central-Tendency"><a href="#Leniency-Errors-Strictness-Error-Error-Of-Central-Tendency" class="headerlink" title="Leniency Errors, Strictness Error, Error Of Central Tendency"></a>Leniency Errors, Strictness Error, Error Of Central Tendency</h3><p>These are errors where the evaluator has tendencies to either positivelyor negatively evaluate everyone.Remember that professor that gave everyone a B-?</p><p>Unfortunately, I&#39;ve gone through the entire list.In my first job, my manager was too lenient.He was a non-techie manager who only gave positive feedback.During one of my performance reviews, I demanded a mentor (and got it :D).I recently had a client who was too strict and gave evaluations mostly innegatives.He&#39;d always highlight everything that is wrong with your project.No word of thanks or compliments when you fixed them.In a past sprint, when a complement came out of his mouth, the entire team synchronously exclaimed &quot;WHAT DID HE JUST SAY?.&quot;That was a first!My last manager had central tendencies and evaluated everyone in the team to be average.If you screwed up recently, you want to be below average.Upon reflection, I think he was a bit too conservative.</p><p>To avoid this, you need to come up with some kind of strategy.If you evaluate most people in the negative or average,there probably something wrong with your personality.If you evaluate everyone positively all the time,you are not helping them grow.So you need to come up with some kind of strategy.For example, some people scale.</p><p>I personally like to follow a barbel strategy.In terms of giving feedback,I pick 1-3 things that really stood out about their performance and 1-2 sticking points less than or equal to the number of things that stood out.Rest is small talk/filler words.Of course, everyone always does not get to win.For example, where you have been asked to judge at contests.You will sometimes have to rank people.Scoring can work but is time consuming.I have recently found sorting to be an effective strategy in that where I do pairwisecomparisons based on criteria sections and sort people until I reach an ordering that I think is fair.</p><p>Happy evaluatons.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Both formally and informally, we all have to perform evaluations on a daily basis.
Whether it is doing someone&amp;#39;s performance evaluati
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>What Is Leadership?</title>
    <link href="http://nahidakbar.net/2017/12/17/2017-12-17/"/>
    <id>http://nahidakbar.net/2017/12/17/2017-12-17/</id>
    <published>2017-12-17T07:40:50.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-01-12T00:30:50.391Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Saw this meme the other day:</p><p><figure class="figure"><img src="/contents/2017-12-17/boss-leader-engineer.png" alt=""></figure></p><p>Reminded me of some past episodes and made me chuckle.</p><p><s>Leadership has been a subject of interest from the earliest days of human society.</s></p><p>That is wrong!In my mind, leadership something more natural and intrinsic to life.I quite dislike the notion where humans are viewed to be somehow external to or above nature.Sure we don&#39;t live naked in caves and trees any more and we have people in space.However, to get you down from your rocket ship, consider the following: if another big meteor fell on earth tomorrow, most humans will die along with other species in nature we claim superiority over.In addition, regardless of however you define leadership, you will no doubt find examples in non-human species.That is - it is not something unique to or invented by humans.I don&#39;t, however, expect this reflection to be relevant to baboons and naked mole rats.So I also want to keep things practical by not straying too far from my own speciesand my own practice.</p><p>So what is leadership? Let&#39;s check out <a href="http://www.dictionary.com/browse/leadership" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dictionary.com</a>.It defines leadership as:</p><blockquote><p>noun</p><ol><li>the position or function of a leader, a person who guides or directs a group:<blockquote><p>He managed to maintain his leadership of the party despite heavy opposition.</p></blockquote></li><li>ability to lead:<blockquote><p>As early as sixth grade she displayed remarkable leadership potential.</p></blockquote></li><li>an act or instance of leading; guidance; direction:<blockquote><p>They prospered under his strong leadership.</p></blockquote></li><li>the leaders of a group:<blockquote><p>The union leadership agreed to arbitrate.</p></blockquote></li></ol></blockquote><p>After reading that, you have probably agreed to one or more of the definitions and gave them a mental tick of approval.Time to clue you in on something.At least from my perspective, these definitions are all missing a lot of crucial things.That is: why? to what end?I&#39;ve checked at least two other dictionaries and they don&#39;t fare much better.It does not make it better when you define leadership as a process or science or art or rational or irrational.It might have been something so obvious so they decided to not put it in.However, it is the most important thing to me for the following reasons:</p><p>First, it simplifies the problem of leadership. Say there is certain issue,problem X, that needs to be resolved. Which of the following is a betterway of framing this problem? 1) problem is to resolve x through leadinga team of followers or 2) problem is to resolve x. I would take 2 over 1any day of the week. Why? Because - problem solving 101 - it opens up options.With 2, the problem can be solved any way possible. For example, hiringand expert to do the work or, my favourite, going to the root cause of problem Xand eliminating it so that X ceases to be problem.However, with 1, it assumed that a very fixed, potentially ineffective, inefficient or risky methodof accomplishing potentially less than an ideal solution for problem X.</p><p>Second, here are some trick questions for thought: Would a person be less of a leader if he/she:</p><ul><li>resolved the problem without a team following them; or</li><li>lead a large team as opposed to small one; or</li><li>was old or young; or</li><li>was tall or short; or</li><li>was male or female or some other gender; or</li><li>was of white skin colour or black or yellow or...; or</li><li>was superstitious or not; or</li><li>was experienced vs inexperienced; or</li><li>spoke perfect English or not; or</li><li>knew how to spell or not; or</li><li>was good at public speaking or not; or</li><li>lead a diverse team or not; or</li><li>lead a multidisciplinary team or not; or</li><li>was technically literate or not; or</li><li>was a rock star or a peon; or</li><li>followed some mythology or not; or</li><li>consulted a consultant or not; or</li><li>was a subject matter expert or not; or</li><li>owned many slaves or didn&#39;t; or</li><li>was introverted or extroverted; or</li><li>was a born leader or not; or</li><li>was from the royal family or not; or</li><li>insert your stupid leadership criteria here.</li></ul><p>Depending on how biased you are, and trust me everyone is biased in some ways, you may have not liked how some of these sentences were worded.Even I didn&#39;t like listing all these.However, if you change the definition of leadership from things like &quot;influencing/emotional manipulation&quot; and &quot;standing above others&quot; to&quot;bringing positive change&quot; or something more practical, these things stop to matter.</p><p>Third, you get problems when you don&#39;t ask this question.Say the mad king from game of thrones asks his solders to burn everyone in city with wildfire.Should this order be followed? When you ask this question - king is a leader who people pay tax to and follow to keep them safe etc and make countrymore prosperous etc.When they stop doing that, they cease to be their leader.So the mad king gets burned instead.Why am I giving example from a fictional story? I obviously don&#39;t want to piss off real examples.However, these examples are not absent even in developed/lower power distance cultures.For example, you have people in positions of authority sexually abusing people under them.Once again, I am not going to piss of real examples.This also happen in nature.For example, in most tournament species in nature, there are leaders called &quot;alphas&quot; who do whatever they wantin their group.Humans, of-course, are not tournament species and modern human societal values do not condone these forms of power abuse.</p><p>At last, due to these reasons, it is wrong to define leadership something along the lines of standing above others.The best definition of leadership I&#39;ve found so far is in the High Performance Leadership manual fromToastmasters. It goes something along the lines of:</p><blockquote><p>someone assumes a leadership role when someone decides there is a problem, a need or an injustice and takes action to solve the problem, fulfil the need or correct the injustice</p></blockquote><p>These types of definitions are not probably attractive to most people.It does not sound as impressive as &quot;being the chosen one&quot; or&quot;the leader of men&quot; or what not anddoes not bring assciated social validation or financial benefits.Those are typical reasons why most people pursue leadershipand why it has probably become a hundreds of billion dollar industryworldwide.However, I am more attracted to the above definition.I am probably a bit selfishly motvivated in my belief as it doesnot require having a crowd following you to be a leader.Yes, I am no celebrety or thought leader andthe tought creeps me out a little bit.</p><p>At the same time, this kind of drive feels much more authentic to me thanthe trashy literature that gets sold as authentic leadership.It suggests to me that to become a great leader, instead of trying to be agreat leader, you should focus on the problem you are trying to solve,the need you are trying and the injustice you are trying to correct.That is - great leaders aren&#39;t obsessed on being great leaders.They are focused on their objectives, missions, values etc.Only in that context, I can see being able to rally others&#39; supportto be an asset. It should not be an honour or a priviledge.Instead, the leader should be thankful in whatever followership supportthey get for their problem, need or cause.</p><p>Followership, in this context, is also a form of leadership.That is - if you decided that the particular cause is worth your timeand decide that you can provide some value.Leaders, then, should be aknowledged based on the value they personally bring.It takes great wishdom and leadership to sometimes gowith the flow in trying something new contrary to personal experiencewhen someone else is taking the lead and learn from that experiment.Ofcourse, if there is some reason why you think the path you are onwill not work, it is part of leadership let that be known.Malicious compliance is unethical.However, in my book, the only people who are not leaders are people blindlyfollowing orders and processes.People not in control over their own actions.People who don&#39;t ask the question &quot;why?&quot; and &quot;to what end?&quot; .They are just exchanging their followership for salary.Asking &quot;why?&quot; and &quot;to what end?&quot; also leads to asking &quot;how to better?&quot;</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Saw this meme the other day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;figure class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/contents/2017-12-17/boss-leader-engineer.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Research Project - 2</title>
    <link href="http://nahidakbar.net/2017/08/06/2017-08-06/"/>
    <id>http://nahidakbar.net/2017/08/06/2017-08-06/</id>
    <published>2017-08-05T20:40:12.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-01-12T00:30:50.391Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It turned out I was only allowed to do a case study using publicly availablesecondary data.I may have also dodged a bullet there.While reviewing literature, I&#39;ve come across a few too many primary databusiness research papers which were a bit too half-assed.They usually come up with a hypothesis, call up dozen or so people with loadedinterview questions and come up with conclusions based on those answers.While, this is probably sufficient in the realm of social sciences,seems somewhat inadequate in my mind.These would never qualify to be published in computer science journals I usuallyfind myself reading.Also, I find myself arguing with superstitious nutbags about science simplyrepresenting the best of human knowledge and reasoning from time to time.I expect a greater level of effort to be put into research than a dozen phonecalls.10000 is a much better number!</p><p>I finally decided to go with something along the lines of &quot;application of financial forecasting for entrepreneurial opportunity recognition&quot; for myresearch topic.It wasn&#39;t easy to come up with a topic.I think I&#39;ve read a few too many Nassim Talib books.That guy hates forecasting with his entire being and I tend to agree with alot of his ideas.From how the preliminary data analysis is looking, I&#39;d say that my studywill produce very similar conclusions.</p><p>I am happy with the topic.Judging by my colleagues&#39; stated background and their comments, mine is probablyone of the broadest topics in my group.Although, I initially proposed something much broader.I wanted to do some impact analysis on the side.Feedback, that came two weeks too late, stated that I should shorten it.Pivoted to my current topic which is half of what I originally proposed.Took two weeks off from work to focus exclusively on it.I am now back on track.Just gotta finish data analysis and complete my report write-up.</p><p>I&#39;ve fallen back to python for this research project.This makes modelling so much easier.I usually just use JavaScript or Golang these days at work.I had completely forgotten how much more productive python was.If I want to do something crazy like model some time series data with thelogistic map, and use that to produce forecasts, it&#39;s only a dozen or so linesof scipy code.</p><p>Back to work tomorrow.Went through my email today and it looks like I&#39;ll have to hit the groundrunning.Gonna do some meal planning today so I can free up more time for the researchstudy.Only two and half weeks left to finalise my work and submit report.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;It turned out I was only allowed to do a case study using publicly available
secondary data.
I may have also dodged a bullet there.
While
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Research Project - 1</title>
    <link href="http://nahidakbar.net/2017/07/05/2017-07-05/"/>
    <id>http://nahidakbar.net/2017/07/05/2017-07-05/</id>
    <published>2017-07-04T20:40:12.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-01-12T00:30:50.391Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#39;ve been having a bit of hard time on deciding on a research topic to finishoff my masters project.Doing something with secondary data seems like it will be perfect for savingtime and would play to my strengths.At the same time, I feel as through I should push myself a bit out of mycomfort zone and try something a bit more full on.I&#39;ll have to make a decision in the next week or so.</p><p>I&#39;ve started going through the textbook (Saunders et al on research methods).Have only gone through the first chapter and seems to be a good read so far.Few things stood out for me:</p><p>Firstly, it differentiates <strong>methods</strong> and <strong>methodology</strong>.Methods, it argues, are simply techniques and procedures.Methodology, in contrast, relate to the theory of how it should be conducted.For example, a survey would be a method.In contrast, the rationale behind if a survey would be an appropriate methodfor a research problem would be methodology.</p><p>Secondly, it defined important characteristics of research.Research, it argued, is not simply information collection and reportinng onthese.For example, if you interviewed a bunch of people and released a report of youropinions on what the data you collected means, you can&#39;t call it research.Even through, the activities are the same, for something to be research, itneeds to fulfil the following conditions:</p><ul><li>There must be a clear purpose</li><li>Data must be collected systematically</li><li>Data must be interpreted systematically</li></ul><p>Systematically implies basis on logical relationships, not on beliefs andopinions.In the above case, for example, it would be valid research if the interviewwas an appropriate method to logically infer the research of results.</p><p>For example, a research problem might be to deduce if all managers are lazy.If someone interviewed a 10000 managers and determined each one of them tobe lazy, and reported on this result, it will not be enough to show thatall managers are lazy.It can only logically prove that some managers are lazy.All managers could only be lazy if it can be proved that those 10000 managersinterviewed represent all possible types of managers, such as, hard workingmanagers, fat managers, tall managers, unicycle riding managers etc.</p><p>You&#39;d also need to be very clear about what you mean by lazy.For example, my parents think I am lazy as I &quot;play on my computer all day.&quot;When they think &quot;hard working,&quot; perhaps an image similar to farmers diggingholes in barren land come to their mind.My employers, on the other hand, is somewhat grateful that I spend on day infront of a computer and would interpret it differently.</p><p>Thirdly, it provided a framework for considering relevance gap.It organised research across two dimensions:</p><table><thead><tr><th></th><th>Low Theoretical Rigour</th><th>High Theoretical Rigour</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td><strong>High Practical Relevance</strong></td><td>Popularist Science</td><td>Pragmatic Science</td></tr><tr><td><strong>Low Practical Relevance</strong></td><td>Puerile Science</td><td>Pedantic Science</td></tr></tbody></table><p>In this view, relevance gap exist between the top and bottom rows.I liked how it used the word &quot;puerile&quot; to describe science that has littlepractical relevance and is not rigorous.</p><p>Fourthly, it presented four modes of knowledge creation where researchobjectives are determined by:</p><table><thead><tr><th>Mode</th><th>Objectives determined by</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Mode 1</td><td>academic interests</td></tr><tr><td>Mode 2</td><td>practical needs</td></tr><tr><td>Mode 0</td><td>sponsor&#39;s interests</td></tr><tr><td>Mode 3</td><td>survival and common good</td></tr></tbody></table><p>There was more info on maintaining reflexive diaries etc.</p><p>Hoping to cover more ground on the book before settling on a topic and furtherplanning.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been having a bit of hard time on deciding on a research topic to finish
off my masters project.
Doing something with secondary 
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Janus - Software Engineering Diagramming Tool</title>
    <link href="http://nahidakbar.net/2017/04/30/2017-04-30/"/>
    <id>http://nahidakbar.net/2017/04/30/2017-04-30/</id>
    <published>2017-04-29T20:40:12.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-01-12T00:30:50.391Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#39;ve been putting some of my free time into a new open source project called Janus. It is meant to be a diagramming tool for various activities around software projects. Frankly, I am just writing this tool for myself.</p><p>Imagine the following very common scenario. You go into a meeting with some new clients. Things run very smoothly. They are excited about getting their product from you. You are excited about building their product for them. You decide that you are going to start working on this as soon as the paperwork is done. And after doing some basic requirements analysis at the start, you discover that you didn&#39;t even ask that very basic question that you need to start.</p><p>Well, it is not really your fault. Normal human brain does not work in detailed lists. The problem is more the fact that the you did not do your analysis early enough.</p><p>Here is a tool for doing so! I am hoping to turn it into something that can greatly assist engineers in real time in generating questions and doing basic analysis to make these sessions more effective.</p><p>It still has a <a href="http://janus.nahidakbar.net" target="_blank" rel="noopener">long way to go</a>.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been putting some of my free time into a new open source project called Janus. It is meant to be a diagramming tool for various 
      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Hello World</title>
    <link href="http://nahidakbar.net/2017/03/04/2017-03-04/"/>
    <id>http://nahidakbar.net/2017/03/04/2017-03-04/</id>
    <published>2017-03-03T19:40:12.000Z</published>
    <updated>2018-01-12T00:30:50.391Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Let&#39;s start a blog! And see what happens.</p>]]></content>
    
    <summary type="html">
    
      
      
        &lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#39;s start a blog! And see what happens.&lt;/p&gt;

      
    
    </summary>
    
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
